The next thing we're going to look at is
how to compute modular large integers. So
我们接下来要看的是如何计算大整数的模
the first question is how do we represent
large integers in a computer? So that's
首先我们要探讨如何在计算机中表示大整数
actually fairly straightforward. So
imagine we're on a 64 bit machine, what we
这实际上相当简单 所以想象我们在操作64比特的机器
would do is we would break the number we
want to represent, into 32 bit buckets And
我们要做的是去分解这个我们要表示的数 32位一组
then, we will basically have these n/32 bit buckets, and together they will
然后我们就会有n/32个组 它们将
represent the number that we want to store
on the computer. Now, I should mention
表示我们想要在计算机上储存的数 现在我要提到
that I'm only giving 64 bit registers as
an example. In fact, many modern
我只是给出一个64位寄存器作为例子 事实上 很多现代的
processors have 128 bit registers or more,
and you can even do multiplications on
处理器拥有128比特或更多比特的寄存器 你甚至可以用它们做乘法
them. So normally you would actually use
much larger blocks than just 32 bits. The
所以通常情况下你 会使用比32位更大的块
reason, by the way, you want to limit
yourself to 32 bits is so that you can
原因是 顺便一说 你想要将你自己限制在32比特的块中这样你就可以将
multiply two blocks together, and the
result will still be less than 64 bits,
两个块相乘，结果仍然会小于64比特
less than the word size on the machine. So
now let's look at particular arithmetic
比机器的字长要短 所以让我们看看特定的算术运算
operations and see how long each one
takes. So addition and subtraction
然后看看每个需要多长 说到加法和减法
basically what you would do is that
addition would carry or subtraction would
基本上你要做的就是加法会进位或者减法会借位
borrow and those are basically linear time
operations. In other words, if you want to
这些基本上是线性时间的操作 换句话说 如果你想要
add or subtract two n bit integers the
running time is basically
加或者减两个n比特整数 运算时间基本上
linear in n. Multiplication
naively will take quadratic time. In fact,
是关于n线性的 乘法运算将需要平方级的时间 事实上
this is what's called the high school algorithm
algorithm. This is what you kind of
这些算法被称为高中算法 这就是你在学校
learned in school, where if you think
about this for a minute you'll see that,
稍微学过的东西 如果你花时间考虑几分钟你会发现
that algorithm basically is quadratic in
the length of the numbers that are being
这个算法基本上就是两个乘数长度的二次方
multiplied. So a big surprise in the 1960s
was an algorithm due to Karatsuba that
所以1960年代的一个大惊喜来是自Karatsuba的算法
actually achieves much better than
quadratic time in fact, it achieved a
它能达到比二次时间更高的效率 事实上，它达到了
running time of n to the 1.585. And
there's actually no point in me showing
n^1.585的运行时间 事实上我向你展示这个算法
you how the algorithm actually worked,
I'll just mention the main idea What
如何运作是没有意义的 我就提一下Karastuba的发现里的
Karatsuba realized, is that in fact when
you want to multiply two numbers, you can
主要思想 就是如果你乘两个数 你可以
write them as, you can take the first
number x, write it as 2 to the b times
把它们写作 你可以把第一个数字x 写作(2^b)*x2+x1
x2 plus x1. Where x2 and x1 are roughly
the size of the square root of x. Okay, so
x2和x1大约是x的平方根的大小
we can kind of break the number x into the
left part of x and the right part of x.
我们可以把数x分成x的左半部分和x的右半部分
And basically, you're writing x as if it
was written base 2 to the b. So it's got
基本上你 你写x就像是写2^b 所以
two digits base 2 to the b. And you do
the same thing with, y. You write y base
这里有两个数字2^b 然后你对数字y做同样的操作 你用2^b表示y
2 to the b. Again, you would write it
as, the sum of the left half plus the
同样的 你应该把它写成 左半部分和右半部分的和
right half, And then, normally, if you try
to do this multiplication, when you open
然后通常情况下 如果你试着做这个乘法 如果你打开
up the parentheses. You see that, this
would require 4 multiplications, right?
这个括号 你看它会需要四次乘法
It would require x2 times y2, x2 times y1,
x1 times y2, and x1 times y1. What
它需要x2*y2，x2*y1，x1*y2，和x1*y1
Karatsuba realized is there's a way to do
this multiplication of x by y using only
Karatsuba发现有一种做这个乘法的方法只需要
three multiplications of x1 x2 y1 y2. So it's just a big multiplication of x times y
乘三次x1 x2 y1 y2 所以它只是一个x*y的大乘法
only it takes three little multiplications. You can now recursively
只需要3次简单的乘法 你现在可以递归地
apply exactly the same procedure to
multiplying x2 by y2, and x2 by y1, and so
应用相同的过程来乘x2和y2，还有x2和y1 等等
on and so forth. And you would get this
recursive algorithm. And if you do the
你会得到这个递归算法 如果你
recursive analysis, you will see that
basically, you get a running time of n to the 1.585.
做一下递归分析 你会发现基本上你会用到n^1.585的运行时间
This number is basically, the 1.585 is basically, log of 3 base 2.
这个数基本上是 1.585基本上是以2为底3的对数
Surprisingly, it turns out that Karatsuba
isn't even the best multiplication
令人惊讶的是 原来Karatsuba在这里也不是最好的乘法
algorithm out there. It turns out that, in fact, you
can do multiplication in about nlog(n) time.
算法 事实证明 你可以在约为n*logn的时间内做乘法
So you can do multiplication in almost linear time.
However, this is an extremely asymptotic results.
所以你几乎可以在线性时间里做乘法 然而,这是一个极其近似结果。
The big O here hides very big constants. And as a
这里的大写O隐藏着很大的常量 而且作为结果来说
result, this algorithm only becomes
practical when the numbers are absolutely
这个算法仅仅在数绝对庞大的时候有用
enormous. And so this algorithm is
actually not used very often. But
所以实际上这种算法并不经常被使用
Karatsuba's algorithm is very practical.
And in fact, most crypto-libraries
但是Karatstba的算法就非常实用 事实上 很多密码类库
implement Karatsuba's algorithm for
multiplication. However, for simplicity
使用Karatsuba的算法做乘法 然而 为了简单一些
here, I'm just gonna ignore Karatsuba's
algorithm, and just for simplicity, I'm
我准备忽略Karatsuba的算法 只是为了简单起见
gonna assume that multiplication runs in
quadratic time. But in your mind, you
我要假设这乘法在平方级时间内运行 但是在你脑海里
should always be thinking all multiplication really is a little bit faster than quadratic.
你要时刻记得所有乘法运算都是比平方级时间要快的
And then the next question after multiplication is what about
然后乘法后的下一个问题是关于
division with remainder and it turns out
that's also a quadratic time algorithm.
有余除法 原来这也是个平方级时间的运算
So the main operation that remains, and one
that we've used many times so far, and
所以主要操作不变 而且也是我们用过很多次的
I've never, actually never, ever told you
how to actually compute it, is this
我从未 确实从未 曾经告诉你们该如何去计算它 这是
question of exponentiation. So let's solve
this exponentiation problem a bit more
一个有关幂运算的问题 所以让我们来更加抽象地解决这个幂运算的问题
abstractly. So imagine we have a finite
cyclic group G. All this means is that
想象我们有一个有限循环群G 这意味着
this group is generated from the powers of
some generator little g. So for example
这个群由一些有限生成元g的幂产生 比如
think of this group as simply ZP, and think of little g as some generator of
简单想象这个群Z*_p 想象小g作为大G的某个生成元
big G. The reason I'm sitting in this way,
is I'm, I want you to start getting used
我这样做的原因是 我希望你可以习惯
to this abstraction where we deal with a
generic group G and ZP really is just
这个抽象概念 我们在处理一般的群G 而ZP真的只是
one example of such a group. But, in fact,
there are many other examples of finite
这种群的一个例子 但是 事实上 还有很多其他有限循环群的例子
cyclic groups. And again I want to
emphasis basically that group G, all it
我还要重申基本上这个群G 只简单地
is, it's simply this powers of this
generator up to the order of the group.
是这个生成元的幂数排列到群的阶数组成的群
I'll write it as G to the Q. So our goal
now is given this element g, and some
我将它写成g的q次方 所以现在我么的目标是基于这种元素g 和一些
exponent x, our goal is to compute the
value of g to the x. Now normally what you
指数x 我们的目标是计算g^x的值 所以通常
would say is, you would think well, you
know, if x is equal to 3  then I'm
你要说 你要想的是 如果 x=3
gonna compute you know, g cubed. Well,
there's really nothing to do. All I do is
然后我将去计算g立方 这真的没什么关系
I just do g times g times g and I get g
cubed, which is what I wanted. So that's
我要做的只是g乘g乘g 然后我得到了g的立方 这就是我要的
actually pretty easy. But in fact, that's
not the case that we're interested in. In
所以这是很简单的 但是实际上 这不是我们感兴趣的东西
our case, our exponents are gonna be
enormous. And so if you try, you know,
对我们来说 我们的指数会是很大的 而且如果你去尝试
think of like a 500-bit number and so if
you try to compute g to the power of a
想象一个500比特的数 如果你试着去计算g的一个五百比特数的次方
500-bit number simply by multiplying g by
g by g by g this is gonna take quite a
只是简单地做乘法g乘g乘g乘g 这需要很长时间
while. In fact it will take exponential
time which is not something that we want
事实上它将花费指数级的时间 这不是我们想要的
to do. So the question is whether even
though x is enormous, can we still compute
所以问题是尽管x非常大 我们是否依然能够比较快地计算出
g to the x relatively fast and the answer
is yes and the algorithm that does that
g^x 答案是可以的 相应的算法
is called a repeated squaring algorithm.
And so let me show you how repeated
叫做重复平方算法 现在让我向你们展示下重复平方算法是如何工作的
squaring works. So let's take as an
example, 53. Naively you would have to do
让我们看一个例子 x=53 你将要计算
53 multiplications of g by g by g by g
until you get to g by the 53 but I want to
53个g的乘积 g*g*g... 直到第53个g 但是我想向你们
show you how you can do it very quickly.
So what we'll do is we'll write 53 in
展示如何能很快的完成它 我们要做的是 将53写成二进制
binary. So here this is the binary
representation of 53. And all that means
所以这就是53的二进制表示 这意味着
is, you notice this one corresponds to 32,
this one corresponds to 16, this one
注意这个1代表32 这个1代表16
corresponds to 4, and this one
corresponds to 1. So really 53 is 32
这个1代表4 这个1代表1 所以事实上
plus 16 plus 4 plus 1. But what
that means is that g to the power of 53 is
53=31+16+4+1 这意味着g^53=g^(32+16+4+1)
g to the power of 32+16+4+1. And we can
break that up, using again, the rules of
我们可以把它分开 再一次使用指数的运算法则
exponentiation. We can break that up as g
to the 32 times g to the 16 times g to the
我们可以把那个分成(g^32)*(g^16)*(g^4)*(g^1)
4 times g to the 1, Now that should start
giving you an idea for how to compute g to
现在这应该能给你一个如何快速计算g^53的主意了
the 53 very quickly. What we'll do is,
simply, we'll take g and we'll start
我们要做的就是 简单地 将g平方
squaring it. So what square wants, g wants
to get g squared. We square it again to
得到g^2 再将它平方得到g^4
get g to the 4, turn g to the 8.
Turn g to the 16, g to the 32. So
再得到g^8 g^16 g^32
we've computed all these squares of g. And
now, what we're gonna do is we're simply
所以我们已经计算完了所有对g的平方 现在我们要做的是
gonna multiply the appropriate powers to
give us the g to the 53. So this is g to
将合适的幂相乘来得到g^53 也就是
the one times g to the 4 times g to the 16 times g to the 32, is basically
(g^1)*(g^4)*(g^16)*(g^32)
gonna give us the value that we want,
which is g to the 53. So here you see that
这就得到了我们想要的值 也就是g^53 所以在这你看到
all we had to do was just compute, let's
see, we had to do one, two, three, four,
我们所做的仅是计算 看一下 我们要做1 2 3 4
five squaring, plus four more multiplications
so with 9 multiplications we computed g
5次平方 加上4次额外的乘法 所以通过9次乘法运算 我们计算出了
to the 53. Okay so that's pretty
interesting. And it turns out this is a
g^53 这很有趣 而且这是一个普遍的现象
general phenomena that allows us to raise
g to very, very high powers and do it very
我们能够很快地将g的幂数升到非常高
quickly. So let me show you the algorithm,
as I said this is called the repeated
让我给你们演示一下这个算法 正如我说过的 这叫做重复平方算法
squaring algorithm. So the input to the
algorithm is the element g and the
这个算法的输入是元素g
exponent x. And the output is g to the x.
So what we're gonna do is we're gonna
和指数x 输出是g^x 我们要做的是
write x in binary notation. So let's say
that x has n bits. And this is the actual
将x写成二进制记法 让我们假设x有n位
bit representation of x as a binary
number. And then what we'll do is the
这就是x的二进制表示 然后我们做如下事情
following. We'll have these two registers.
y is gonna be a register that's constantly
我们要使用两个寄存器 y是一个总做平方的寄存器
squared. And then z is gonna be an
accumulator that multiplies in the
z是一个累加器 它将所需的不同次幂的g相乘
appropriate powers of g as needed. So all
we do is the following we loop through the
我们要做的就是按照x的位循环遍历
bits of x starting from the least
significant bits, And then we do the
从最低位开始 然后我们这样做
following: in every iteration we're simply
gonna square y. Okay, so y just keeps on
在每次迭代中我们就将y平方 所以y在每次迭代中
squaring at every iteration. And then
whenever the corresponding bit of the
一直被平方 然后当指数x中相应位数为1时
exponent x happens to be one, we simply
accumulate the current value of y into
我们就将y的当前值累乘到
this accumulator z and then at the end, we
simply output z. That's it. That's the
累加器z中 最后输出z 就是这样
whole algorithm, and that's the repeated
squaring algorithm. So, let's see an
这就是整个算法 这就是重复平方算法
example with G to the 53. So,
you can see the two columns. y is one
让我们看一个g^53的例子 大家看这两列
column, as it evolves through the
iterations, and z is another column, again
每次迭代y的变化是一列 z是另一列
as it evolves through the iterations. So,
y is not very interesting. Basically, all
表示它在迭代过程中的变化 y不是很有意思 基本上
that happens to y is that at every
iteration, it simply gets squared. And so
每轮迭代y的变化就是被平方
it just walks through the powers of two
and the exponents and that's it. z is the
所以它以2的次数为指数变化
more interesting register where what it
does is it accumulates the appropriate
z是一个更有趣的寄存器 它所做的是 只要指数相应位为1
powers of g whenever the corresponding bit
to the exponent is one. So for example the
就将相应幂的g指数累乘 比如
first bit of the exponent is one,
therefore, the, at the end of the first
指数的第一位是1 所以第一次迭代后
iteration the value of z is simply equal to
g. The second bit of the exponent is zero
z的值为g 指数的第二位为0
so the value of z doesn't change after the
second iteration. And at the end of the
所以第二次迭代后z的值不发生变化 第三次迭代后
third iteration well the third bit of the
exponent is one so we accumulate g to the
因为指数的第三位是1 所以我们将g^4乘进z
fourth into z. The next bit of the
exponent is zero so z doesn't change. The
指数的下一位是0 所以z不会变化
next bit of the exponent is one and so now
we're supposed to accumulate the previous
指数的再下一位是1 所以我们应该将前面的y值
value of y into the accumulator z so let
me ask you so what's gonna be the value of z?
乘进累加器z 让我来问你 z的值将会是多少
Well, we simply accumulate g to the
16 into z and so we simply compute the sum
我们将g^16累乘进z 计算出
of 16 and 5 we get g to the 21.
Finally, the last bit is also set to one
16+5 然后我们得到了g^21 最后一位也是1
so we accumulate it into z, we do 32 plus 21 and we get the finally output g to the 53.
所以我们把它乘进z 计算32+21 就得到了最终的输出g^53
Okay, so this gives you an idea of how
this repeated squaring algorithm works.
这就是一个重复平方算法如何进行的思路
It's is quite an interesting algorithm and
it allows us to compute enormous powers of
这是一个挺有趣的算法 它允许我们以非常非常快的速度计算
g very, very, very quickly. So the number
of iterations here, essentially, would be
g的极高次幂 所以这里迭代的次数 本质上将会是
log base 2 of x. Okay. You notice the
number of iterations simply depends on the
以2为底x的对数 你会注意到迭代的次数仅取决于
number of digits of x, which is basically
the log base 2 of x. So even if  x is a
x的二进制位数 也就是log_2(x) 所以就算x有
500 bit number in 500 multiplication,
well, 500 iterations, really 1,000
500位 要做500次乘法 也就是500迭代 实际上是1000乘法
multiplications because we have to square
and we have to accumulate. So in 1,000
因为我们必须进行平方和累乘 所以通过1000次乘法运算
multiplications we'll be able to raise g
to the power of a 500 bit exponent.
我们能够将指数g的幂升到500位
Okay so now we can summarize kind of the running times so suppose we
好 现在我们能够总结出它的运行时间 假设我们
have an N bit modulus capital N as we
said addition and subtraction in ZN takes
有一个n位模 正如我们说过的 zn上的加减法需要线性时间
linear time. Multiplication of just, you
know, as I said, Karatsuba's actually makes this
乘法 我说过 Karatsuba让乘法计算更有效
more efficient, but for simplicity we'll
just say that it takes quadratic time. And
但是为了简单起见 我们仅说乘法需要平方级时间
then exponentiation, as I said, basically
takes log of x iterations, and at each
然后指数运算 基本上需要logx次迭代
iteration we basically do two
multiplications. So it's O(log (x))
在每一次迭代中 我们做两次乘法 所以是O(log (x)*T(x))
times the time to multiply. And let's say
that the time to multiply is quadratic. So
让我们说乘法需要的是平方级时间
the running time would be, really, N
squared log x. And since x is always gonna
所以运行时间将会是(n^2)logx 根据Fermat定理 x总是会比N小
be less than N, by Fermat's theorem
there's no point in raising g to a power
所以没有必要去计算g大于模数次的幂
that's larger than the modulus. So x is
gonna be less than N. Let's suppose that x
所以x会比N小 让我们假设
is also an N-bit integer, then, really
exponentiation is a cubic-time algorithm.
x也是N位整数 那么 实际上指数运算是立方级时间算法
Okay so that's what I wanted you to
remember, that exponentiation is actually
这是我想让你们记住的 指数运算实际上速度
a relatively slow. These days, it actually
takes a few microseconds on a modern
比较慢 现在 它在现代计算机上实际需要几毫秒
computer. But still, microseconds for a,
for a, say a four gigahertz processor is
但是 毫秒对比如说一个4Ghz的处理器来说依然
quite a bit of work. And so just keep in
mind that all the exponentiation
是很大的工作量 所以要记住所有我们讨论的
operations we talked about. For example,
for determining if a number is a quadratic
指数运算操作 比如 判断一个数是否是二次剩余的
residue or not, All those, all those
exponentiations basically take cubic time.
所有这些 所有指数运算基本上都花费立方级时间
Okay, so that completes our discussion of
arithmetic algorithms, and then in the
好了 这就完成了我们对算术算法的讨论
next segment we'll start talking about
hard problems, modulo, primes and composites.
在下一节我们将开始讨论困难问题 模数运算 质数和合数